我 是 你 的 人
I'M YOUR MAN
- 歡迎   - 你好
- Welcome.   - Hello.
費爾瑟博士
Dr. Felser.
請  跟我來
Please follow me.
你好  艾瑪  我是湯姆
Hi, Alma. I'm Tom.
很高興見到你  艾瑪
Nice to meet you, Alma.
我們坐下談談吧
Shall we sit down?
你要喝點什麼
What can I bring you to drink?
波爾多葡萄酒很不錯哦
The Bordeaux is a real treat.
要波爾多葡萄酒嗎
Bordeaux for the lady?
你非常溧亮  艾瑪
You're a very beautiful woman, Alma.
你的眼睛就像兩個山中的湖泊  我可以沉入其中
Your eyes are like two mountain lakes I could sink into.
湯姆  對吧
Tom, right?
你不喜歡別人的讚美嗎
Don't you like compliments?
你相信上帝嗎
Do you believe in God?
這不是討論這種問題的地方
This is hardly the place to discuss such a question.
(賴內.馬利亞.里爾克  奧地利著名詩人)
- 你有最喜歡的詩嗎   - 我特別喜歡里爾克
- Do you have a favorite poem?   - I particularly like Rilke.
例如《秋日》
Autumn Day, for example.
第六和第七行是什麼
Sixth and seventh lines?
催促它們向盡善盡美成長  並把最後的甜蜜釀進濃酒
"Press them to ripeness, and chase The last sweetness into the heavy wine."
- 這首詩倒數第二個字母是什麼   - E
- Second to last letter of the poem?   - E.
- 生命的意義是什麼   - 讓世界變得更美好
- What is the meaning of life?   - To make the world a better place.
3587乘以982除以731等於多少
3,587 times 982, divided by 731?
4,818.65116.
你能想到的最悲傷的事情是什麼
What is the saddest thing you can think of.
孤獨地死去
Dying alone.
我們跳舞吧  倫巴舞
Shall we dance? Rumba!
我建議你不要拒絕這個機會  費爾瑟博士
I suggest you take advantage of the opportunity, Dr. Felser.
你會大吃一驚的
You will be amazed.
我做錯了什麼嗎
Am I doing something wrong?
我...我...
I am... I am...
請原諒這種複雜情況
Please excuse this complication.
但是我向你保證  這種型號出現這樣的情況非常罕見
But I assure you, it's extremely rare with this model.
就像中彩票一樣罕見
As rare as winning the lottery.
我的意思是  就概率而言
I mean, in terms of probability.
我向你保證  我們的技術人員明天晚上會把一切都處理妥當
I assure you, our technicians will have everything in order by tomorrow night.
對於這次令人不快的耽擱  我們感到非常抱歉
We are so sorry for this unpleasant delay.
沒關係
No problem.
你不知道編寫調情程序有多難
You have no idea how hard it is to program flirting.
只需一個錯誤的舉動  一個誤導的目光  一句不經意的話
One false move, one misleading glance, one careless remark,
然後浪漫就煙消雲散了  我說的對嗎
and the romance evaporates. Am I right?
這整個佈置可能看起來有點奢侈
This whole setting might seem a bit extravagant,
但這種浪漫的邂逅為我們的最終調整提供了寶貴的信息
but this romantic encounter gives us valuable input for the final adjustments.
即使你是三個星期內測試湯姆的十位專家之一
And even though you're one of ten experts testing Tom for just three weeks,
但你們第一次見面的氣氛是非常重要的
the atmosphere of your first encounter is of utmost importance.
- 那可是很費力的事   - 沒有你想的那麼費力
- That's a lot of effort.   - Not as much as you think.
全息成像
Holograms.
它們更便宜  而且可以跳得更久
They're cheaper and they can dance longer.
我知道你帶著某種超然的情緒來看待這件事
I know you see this with a certain emotional detachment,
作為一個測試者  你應該這樣做
which you should as a test person,
但我強烈建議你敞開心扉接受這種體驗
but I highly recommend that you open yourself up to this experience.
當幸福來敲門時  你不該將其拒之門外
When happiness knocks at your door, you should open it.
明天可是個大日子
Tomorrow's the big day.
一切都將配置好  然後你可以把湯姆帶回家了
Everything will be configured, and you can take Tom home.
好的  謝謝
Okay, thanks.
- 你好  朱莉安   - 你好  艾瑪
- Hello, Juliane.   - Hello, Alma.
抱歉  我有事耽擱了  你們不會想知道的
Sorry, I got held up. You don't want to know.
我馬上要在出去一趟  2202掃瞄完成了嗎
I have to go again in a second, too. Is scan 2202 done?
是的  在桌子上
Yes, it's on the desk.
剩下的時間不多了  這是最後的衝刺了
There's not much time left. It's the final sprint.
- 明天見   - 明天見
- See you tomorrow.   - See you.
他們測試我  掃瞄我的大腦  給我不間斷的調查
They test me, scan my brain, give me non-stop surveys,
然後他們輸入
then they feed those things
來自一千七百萬人的所謂思維文件
with so-called mind files from 17 million people:
特徵  觀點  感覺
traits, views, feelings...
超級複雜  天知道要花多少錢
It's super complex, and God knows how much it costs.
結果是什麼
And what's the result?
「你的眼睛就像兩個山中的湖泊  我可以沉入其中」
"Your eyes are like two mountain lakes I could sink into."
也許他們比你更了解你自己
Maybe they know you better than you know yourself.
我很想試試
I'd love to try it.
- 你設計了你的理想伴侶嗎   - 是的
- Have your dream girl built for you?   - Yeah.
但是我已經把她帶回家了  不開玩笑了
But I've already got her at home. All joking aside.
不管我們怎樣想
Regardless of our opinion,
我是倫理委員會的成員  我需要你的評估
I'm on the ethics committee and I need your evaluation.
- 我已經知道夠多了  現在就可以寫報告   - 艾瑪  這是關於
- I've seen enough to write it.   - Alma, this is about
這些東西是否會被允許結婚  工作
whether these things will be allowed to marry, to work,
拿到護照  人權  或者部分人權  或者...
to get passports, human rights, or partial human rights or...
羅傑  我...
Roger, I...
我不知道...
Oh, I didn't know that...
抱歉  你好  艾瑪
Sorry. Hello, Alma.
你好  朱利安
Hello, Julian.
嗯  那...
Um, it...
其實不急  我一會兒再來
It's not urgent. I'll come back.
好的  回頭見
Okay, see you later.
- 為什麼不讓朱利安去做   - 單身是先決條件
- Why can't Julian do it?   - Being single is a prerequisite.
- 弗蘭克呢   - 艾瑪
And Frank? -Alma.
每個人要就都已經成家了  要就有伴侶
Everyone either has a family or a partner.
你也同意了設計成你理想伴侶
You agreed to this, and your thing, your dream partner,
而且已經為你準備好了  只需三個星期而已
has already been built for you. It's just three weeks.
然後你和你的團隊就可以飛到芝加哥  親眼看到楔形文字的碑文
Then you and your crew can fly to Chicago and see the cuneiform tablets in person.
我來提供資金
I'll allocate the funds.
別多想  這不是賄賂
No, no, it's not a bribe.
只是一點小小的感謝
Just a little thank you.
- 好久不見  你最近去了那兒   - 那兒都去了
- Long time no see. Where have you been?   - Here and there.
去哥本哈根的參加會議  博物館...
A convention in Copenhagen, the museum...
- 嗨  艾瑪   - 嗨  雷吉娜
- Hi, Alma!   - Hi, Regina.
- 嘿  朱利安   - 嘿
- Hey, Julian.   - Hey.
- 你好嗎   - 很好
- How are you?   - Okay.
你呢
And you?
我們找個時間去喝杯咖啡  聊聊吧
Let's go for a coffee sometime, talk a little.
我要走了  回頭見
I have to go. See you soon.
- 是柯拉嗎   - 是艾瑪
- Cora?   - It's Alma.
你在裏面幹什麼
What are you doing in there?
把賣的東西放好
Putting away groceries.
我不需要
I don't need groceries!
我知道  爸爸  就像你不需要吃東西一樣
I know, Dad, just like you don't need anything to eat.
不要把我當小孩子對待
Don't treat me like a child.
但今天是星期四  我每個星期四都會來打擾你的
But it's Thursday. I bother you every Thursday.
啊  又在室內抽煙嗎
Ah, smoking in stereo again?
柯拉死了嗎
Is Cora dead?
據我所知沒死
Not as far as I know.
但是她每周四都去足球場接尼科
But she picks Nico up from soccer on Thursdays.
尼科就是那個孩子
Nico is the child.
是的
Yup.
醜得要命的那個
The ugly one.
爸爸
Dad!
你今天是不可能把我帶到外面去的
There's no way you're getting me outside today.
但外面陽光普照啊
But the sun is shining.
去他媽的陽光
Fuck the sun.
看到了吧  其實也沒那麼糟
See? It's not so bad after all.
是的
Yes it is.
- 我患回家   - 再走一段就到
- I want to go home.   - Just a little further. Almost there.
請稍等
One moment, please.
哦  對不起
Oh, I'm sorry.
你好  艾瑪
Hello, Alma.
你和你的院長已經簽署了保密條款
You and your dean have signed the confidentiality clause.
緊急情況下  你可以隨時聯繫我們
In an emergency, you can reach us 24/7.
沒有其它的事的話  那麼我們將在三天後上午十點見面
Otherwise, we'll see each other in three days at 10:00 AM.
- 還有什麼我應該知道的嗎   - 我們建議共享過去
- Is there anything else I should know?   - We recommend working on a shared past.
編一個你們如何相遇的故事
Invent a story about how you met.
為了擁有未來  你需要過去
To have a future, you need a past.
你的品味真不錯
You really have great taste.
謝謝你
Thank you.
你真是太好了
That's very kind of you.
如果你把座椅抬高約十五厘米
If you were to raise your seat about 15 centimeters,
座椅向前傾斜十二度  並將視線向後伸展
tilt your seat 12 degrees forward and extend that look over your shoulder,
發生事故的  可能性將降低27%
the likelihood of an accident would reduce by 27 percent.
我對我提出的關於改善你的安全的建議表示反感
I register an aversion to my advice on improving your safety,
但是...
but also...
也對我正確虛擬語氣的表示認可
to my correct use of the subjunctive.
這樣說對嗎
Is that correct?
失敗的溝通嘗試對於校準我對你的演算法至關重要
Failed communication attempts are crucial for calibrating my algorithm to you.
我可能會做和說一些你拒絕的事情
I may do and say things you reject,
但這樣的錯誤會越來越少
but these mistakes will happen less and less.
很快  我就會以更高的成功率說出和做出你喜歡的事情
Soon I'll say and do things you like with a much higher success rate.
很快  每一次都會直中靶心
Soon every shot will be a bullseye.
好的  這是起居室
Okay, this is the living room,
廚房在這裏...
the kitchen...
這是在那裏拍的
Where was that taken?
不知道  一個朋友拍的
No idea. A friend took it.
一個好朋友嗎
A good friend?
我喜歡這顏色
I like the colors.
- 你還需要什麼嗎   - 不用了  謝謝  你真好
- You need anything else?   - No thanks. You're a dear.
哦  廁所在那裏  萬一你...
Oh, the bathroom, in case you...
刷牙  清潔身體  我還是需要的
I brush my teeth and clean my body.
這是你的房間
And this is your room.
我們不用睡在同一張床上嗎
We won't sleep in the same bed?
- 晚安   - 晚安  艾瑪
- Good night, then.   - Good night, Alma.
為什麼是英國口音
Why the English accent?
你會被有點異國情調的男人吸引
You're attracted to men who are slightly foreign.
不是本地人  但又不能太異國化
Not local, but not exotic.
所以就選擇是英國口音了
That'd be British.
早上好  艾瑪
Good morning, Alma.
睡得好嗎
Did you sleep well?
我整理了一下  這樣你就能更容易地找到你的東西了
I tidied up, so you can find your things more easily.
它們是按照一個系統來組織的  例如...
They're organized according to a system, for example...
好的
No problem.
我需要... 十一分鐘把所有東西恢復到原來的位置
I need... 11 minutes to return everything to its initial position.
我馬上要把窗戶恢復到原來的樣子了
I'll dirty up the windows again in a second.
窗戶你就不必恢復了
You can leave the windows.
我沒時間吃早飯  上班要遲到了
I don't have time for breakfast. I'm late for work.
我很期待一次浪漫的早午餐
I was so looking forward to a romantic little brunch.
- 一起聊聊天   - 我從不聊天
- Have a little chat.   - I never chat.
這就是我愛你的原因
And that's why I love you.
聽著  湯姆
Listen, Tom.
我知道你被設計成一個潛在的伴侶
I know you're programmed to be a potential partner.
但是我不能忍受這樣的三個星期
But I can't stand three weeks of this.
我受不了這樣的早晨  我會發瘋的
I can't stand one morning of this. I'll go nuts.
我不是在找伴侶
I'm not looking for a partner.
我只是測試你三個星期  然後寫一份評估報告
I'm just testing you for three weeks and writing an evaluation.
你對愛情一點興趣都沒有嗎
Ah. And love doesn't interest you at all?
- 毫無興趣   - 那溫柔呢
- Zero interest.   - And tenderness?
還有親密的接近  激烈的眼神交流昵
Intimate closeness? Intense eye-contact?
當然沒有
Definitely not.
- 蝴蝶昵   - 沒興趣
- Butterflies?   - No.
- 愛到無法思考了嗎   - 絕對不會
- So much in love you can't think straight?   - Absolutely not.
這就解釋了為什麼要分床睡了
That explains the separate beds.
我建議你離我遠點  我也離你遠點
I suggest you leave me alone, and I leave you alone,
這三個星期  我們都要有尊嚴地度過  好嗎
and we get through these three weeks more or less with dignity, okay?
我設計的演算法就是為了讓你開心
My algorithm is designed to make you happy.
太好了
Great.
那讓我一個人呆著應該沒什麼問題
Then leaving me alone should be no problem at all.
這是讓我最開心的事
That's what makes me happiest.
現在我真的要走了
Now I really have to go.
- 我能和你一起去嗎   - 不行
- Can I come with you?   - No.
我可以幫你
I can help you.
這是一個非常具體的研究項目  你需要幾年的時間來閱讀...
It's a very specific subject. You'd need years to read...
好吧  也許你只需要幾毫秒就能讀懂
Okay, maybe you'd just need milliseconds to read up on it,
但這是關於詩歌和隱喻...
but it's about poetry and metaphors...
我這是在做什麼
What am I doing?
好的  我可以留在這裏
Okay, I can stay here.
讓自己變得有用  讓這個地方變得溧亮
Make myself useful. Make the place nice.
在這兒等我
Wait here for me.
給自己買杯咖啡或一些什麼
Buy yourself a coffee or something.
- 隨便買什麼都可以   - 好的
- Whatever you want.   - Okay.
我會表現得像一個想要東西的人  沒有人會知道其中的區別
I'll act like a person who wants things. No one will know the difference.
- 我一會兒就回來   - 好極了
- I'll be a while.   - Peachy.
你也可以刪除那些花俏的口語
You can also delete: you betcha, okey-dokey and toodeloo.
完成
Done.
你想喝點什麼
Hey, what can I get you?
我今天感覺怎麼樣
What do I feel like today?
想到了  我要一杯中等大小的摩卡奇諾  再加一小杯榛子糖漿
Yes! I'll take a mid-sized mochaccino with a shot of hazelnut syrup.
我今天有點不舒服
I'm feeling a little nutty today.
四元七角  謝謝
4.70, please.
這是五元
Make it 5.00.
你的咖啡在那邊
Your coffee is over there.
這是我們之間的私話
Just between us.
你能猜到我其實什麼都不想要嗎
Would you have guessed that I can't actually want anything?
他們完全忘記了所在的環境
They're totally oblivious of their surroundings.
很瘋狂  對吧
Crazy, right?
他們已經看了四十五分鐘的史詩般的失敗視頻了
They've been watching epic fail videos for 45 minutes.
人們未能實施計劃的片段
Short clips showing footage of people failing to implement a plan.
你能解釋一下這樣有什麼好笑的嗎
Could you explain to me what is funny about that?
我是說
Well, I mean,
只是看到別人絆倒  摔倒或者從什麼東西上摔下來  都很有趣
it's just funny to see someone trip, or fall down, or fall off something.
- 有什麼好笑的嗎   - 看起來很傻
- What is funny about it?   - It looks so silly.
我不知道  我無法解釋
I don't know. I can't explain it.
但是沒有人會死  那就不好笑了
But no one dies. That wouldn't be funny.
- 是這個意思嗎   - 不是  那是絕對不好笑
- Would it?   - No, that definitely wouldn't be funny.
死亡並不好笑  不是嗎
Dying is rarely funny, right?
抱歉花了這麼長時間  我真的很抱歉
Sorry it took so long. I'm really sorry.
- 沒關係   - 我沒想到他們會關門
- No problem.   - I didn't think they'd close.
我以為他們通宵營業昵
I thought they stayed open all night.
對我來說  無論是在咖啡館裏還是站在咖啡館外面都沒什麼分別
It makes no difference to me if I'm in a cafe or standing outside one.
你需要毛巾或其它的嗎
Do you need a towel or something?
我沒事  謝謝
I'll be fine, thanks.
給你
Here.
這樣下次你就不用站在雨中了
So you don't have to stand in the rain next time.
放鬆一點  工作太久對你沒好處
Relax a little. Too much work isn't good for you.
93%的德國女性都夢想著這個呢
93% of German women dream of this.
- 猜猜我屬於那個部分   - 百分之七的那個嗎
- And guess which group I belong to.   - The 7%?
你怎樣這麼快就想明白了昵
How did you figure that out so quickly?
如果你對我好一點  對我敞開心扉  你會感覺好一點的
You'd feel better if you were nice to me, if you opened up to me.
- 你會更開心   - 然後呢
- You'd be happier.   - Then what?
那樣你會更開心
Then you'd be happier.
內啡肽  血清素水平升高  多巴胺釋放...
Endorphins, elevated serotonin levels, dopamine release...
太好了
Yippee.
所有的人都想要快樂
All people want to be happy.
好吧...
Well...
如果這超出了你的演算法的能力  不要感到難過
Don't feel bad if that's beyond your algorithm's capabilities.
畢竟那是屬於人類的
It's human.
湯姆  你能開下門嗎
Tom! Can you get the door?
是送信的
It's the mail.
湯姆
Tom?
- 你好  艾瑪   - 噢
- Hello, Alma.   - Oh!
朱利安一直在聯繫你  這樣他今天就能拿走照片了
Julian has been trying to reach you so he could pick up the picture today.
因為你還在洗澡  所以我給他倒了杯咖啡
And because you were still in the shower, I just offered him a coffee.
是的 他剛剛請我喝咖啡
Yes, he just offered me a coffee.
是的  他剛給你倒了杯咖啡
Yes, he just offered you a coffee.
現在咖啡已經準備好了
And now it's ready.
謝謝
Thanks.
- 湯姆是同事   - 好的  當然  同事
- Tom is a colleague.   - Yes, sure. A colleague.
說實話  在我們見面之前  我就是她的秘密粉絲
To be honest, I was a secret fan of hers even before we met.
我關注她的工作很多年了  她是個國際...
I've been following her work for years. She's an international...
不用解釋  湯姆
It's okay, Tom.
- 你們在那裏認識的   - 哥本哈根
- So where did you meet?   - In Copenhagen.
在人類學大會上
At the Anthropology Convention.
八月份的時候  我告訴過你我在那裏
In August. I told you I was there.
我現在在佩加蒙博物館  我們的工作是相似的
Since I'm at the Pergamon now and our work is similar,
雖然我研究的是波斯楔形文字  而不是蘇美爾楔形文字
although I study Persian and not Sumerian cuneiform,
阿爾瑪說我可以住她的客房
Alma offered me the use of her guest room.
你們的相似之處很豐富嗎  是密集的  還是可以說是纏繞在一起的
And are these similarities fertile? Intensive? Intertwined, so to speak?
朱利安  別鬧了
Julian, please.
這不關我的事
It's none of my business.
那好吧...
Okay then...
照片
The picture.
哇  比我印象中的還要大  我不知道能不能塞進去
Wow, it's bigger than I remember. I have no idea if it'll fit.
- 你開的是什麼車   - 馬尼拉
- What are you driving?   - A Manila.
能塞進去
It'll fit.
馬尼拉是233乘157乘68厘米  照片是210乘170厘米
A Manila is 233 by 157 by 68 centimeters. The picture is 210 by 170 cm.
如果你把它傾斜一下  它就完全能塞進去了
If you tilt it, it'll fit perfectly.
- 好的   - 我來幫你  沒什麼大不了的
- Okay, cool.  - I'll help you. No big deal.
首先我要跳進我的褲子裏
I'll just jump into my pants.
- 我說對了嗎   - 是的  你說對了
- Did I say it right?   - Yes, you did.
別多想  我當然為你高興
No, I'm happy for you, of course.
- 不是你想的那樣   - 你可以騙別人  但我不行
- It's really not what you think.   - You can fool lots of people, but not me.
我知道那種表情  你以前也是這樣看我的
I know that look. You used to look at me that way.
胡說  但我不想吵架  隨便你怎樣想
Nonsense, but I don't want to fight. Believe what you want.
等事情穩定下來  你和史黛菲也可以見見
It would be nice if things calmed down, and you and Steffi could meet, too.
也許你願意參加我們的喬遷宴
Maybe you'd like to come to our housewarming?
- 你要搬家了嗎   - 大部分是因為經濟原因
- You're moving in?   - For financial reasons, mostly.
什麼時候
When?
明天
Tomorrow.
如果你能來我會很高興的
I'd be glad if you came.
我們再說吧
We'll see.
不過還是謝謝你的邀請
But thanks for the invitation.
照片的事我很抱歉
I feel bad about the picture.
別擔心  它已經在這裏掛得夠久了
Don't worry. It's been hanging here long enough.
好吧  那麼...
Okay, then...
你最好什麼話都不要說
It'd be best if you didn't say anything.
當然  我不是說你應該完全保持沉默
Of course I don't mean you should be completely silent.
就說是「倫敦來的同事」就行了
Just say "a colleague from London." That's enough.
他們當然會認為我們...
Of course they'll think that we're...
但他們必須面對這個問題
But they'll just have to deal with that.
- 他是和我一起的   - 好的
- He's with me.   - Okay.
如果你認為天氣很好  而且現在其他人在過周末
If you think the weather's lovely and it's the weekend for everyone else,
那你就對了
you're right.
但至少還有咖啡
But at least there's coffee
還有幾個甜甜圈  如果有人想吃的話
and a few donuts if anyone wants one.
- 帕特裏克  要咖啡嗎   - 好的  謝謝
- Patrick, want a coffee?   - Sure. Thank you.
這是湯姆  他是我在倫敦的同事
This is Tom, a colleague from London.
他研究波斯楔形文字的  但他想看看我們在做什麼
He works with Persian cuneiform, but he wanted to see what we're up to.
- 嗨  湯姆   - 歡迎
- Hi, Tom.   - Welcome.
我該帶湯姆參觀一下嗎  反正我正在上傳的東西慢得很
Should I give Tom a little tour? I'm waiting for a slow upload anyway.
當然  那會很有趣的
Sure, that would be fascinating.
好吧
Okay.
我能佔用你一點時間嗎  我想給你看點東西
Can I grab you for a second? I'd like to show you something.
我不知道你對我們的理論有多熟悉
I don't know how familiar you are with our abstract,
但實際上我們試圖證明即使在公元前四千年
but essentially, we're trying to prove that even in 4,000 BC,
在長期以來被視為純粹行政性的最早書面文本中
in the earliest written texts which have long been seen as purely administrative,
實際上也有詩歌  抒情和隱喻的使用
there was actually poetry, use of lyric and metaphor.
而且那個人並不是只靠麵包生活
And that man does not live by bread alone.
是的  那時候也沒有麵包
Yes. Not even back then.
你看得懂嗎
Can you read it?
波斯楔形文字只有一小部分字符
Persian cuneiform has a fraction of the characters.
- 你熟悉蘇美爾楔形文字嗎   - 是的
- Are you familiar with Sumerian cuneiform?   - Yes.
它只比波斯楔形文字多出二千七百萬種組合
It only has 27 million more combinations than Persian cuneiform.
但這是阿卡德語
But this is Akkadian.
是的  沒錯
Yes, that's right.
我能和你談談嗎
May I speak with you?
- 怎麼了   - 在看碑文的時候
- What's up?   - While looking at the tablets,
我調查了即將出版的刊物  發現了一份來自布宜諾斯艾利斯的研究題目是
I surveyed upcoming publications. I found a study from Buenos Aires titled:
- 什麼  我不會黨西班牙語   - 楔形文字詩歌
- What? I don't speak Spanish.   - The Poetry of Cuneiform:
在公元前二千七百年作為反映社會的隱喻
Metaphor as a Reflection of Society in 2700 BC.
它在 uni服務器上很容易訪問
It's easily accessible on the uni server.
真不敢相信我們竟然不知道這個
I can't believe we didn't know about this!
- 你為什麼這麼生氣   - 你他媽的在開玩笑嗎
- Why are you so upset?   - Are you fucking kidding me?
我為什麼生氣  我研究這個已經三年了
Why I'm upset? I've researched this for three years!
三年了  沒日沒夜  就在我們出版前
Three years, day and night! And right before we publish,
在布宜諾斯艾利斯的某個小妞
comes some chick from Buenos fucking Aires!
也研究了很多年
She's been studying it for years, too!
同樣的事情  同樣的想法
The same thing, the same idea!
只不過她三個月前就出版了
Except she's publishing three months earlier!
這一切都他媽的白費了
This was all for fucking nothing!
三年的研究白費了
Three years of research up in smoke!
這項研究對人們很重要
This study is important for the people.
這表明總是有更深層次的含義
It shows that there was always deeper meaning.
人們總是喜歡玩文字遊戲
That people have always played with words,
總是為了詩歌而寫詩
always created poetry for poetry's sake alone.
人類應該被告知這一點  而且他們也將會被告知
Humanity should be informed of that and they will be.
結果是一樣的
The outcome remains the same.
也許是為了人類  但不是為了我
Maybe for humanity, but not for me.
這不是為了我
Not for me!
所以你眼中的淚水
So the tears in your eyes
只是為你自己和你的事業而流嗎
only relate to yourself and your career?
它們像是以自我為中心的淚水
They're egotistical tears.
艾瑪
Alma?
怎麼回事
What's going on?
對不起
I'm sorry!
我也為你感到抱歉
I'm so sorry for your sakes, too!
讓我來解釋一下
Let me explain.
艾瑪  我想...
Alma, I think...
- 嗨  我是艾瑪  你們是誰   - 你好
- Hi, I'm Alma. Who are you guys?   - Hello.
這是麗塔  勞爾還有...
This is Rita, Raul and...
- 加里   - 加里
- Gary.   - Gary.
你是第一個理解我的人
You're the first man who's ever understood me.
- 我能親你嗎   - 你得問那個女人
- Can I kiss you please?   - You'll have to ask that woman.
我屬於她
I belong to her.
親吧
Go ahead.
- 艾瑪  我...   - 我自己能走
- Alma, I...   - I can walk by myself!
你不想進來嗎
Don't you want to come in?
你不想出來嗎
Don't you want to come out?
你就不能給我一次驚喜嗎
Can't you surprise me for once?
你就不能做點奇怪的事...
Can't you do something weird, something...
一些蠢事什麼的  你就不能別再做正確的事嗎
Something dumb? Can't you stop doing everything right?
- 你不知道你想要什麼   - 是的  我不知道我想要什麼
- You don't know what you want.   - No, I don't know what I want.
有時候就是這樣的
That's how it is sometimes.
當你是人類的時候
When you're human.
你喝醉了
You're drunk.
為你的健康乾杯
Cheers, to your health.
你的老二是怎麼回事
So, what's the deal with your cock?
- 你說什麼   - 還是說只有先接吻後才能做愛  是嗎
- Pardon me?   - Sex only works if you kiss first?
是的
Yes.
或者如果你的傳感器沒有被激活  你就不會...硬起來
Or your sensor isn't activated and you won't get... hard?
沒錯
Exactly.
你生過氣嗎
Do you ever get angry?
你的演算法有這一部分嗎
Is that part of your algorithm?
如果合適的情況下  我相信我可以表現出憤怒之類的情緒
If it seems appropriate, I believe I could display something like anger.
或者是生氣  我從來不明白其中的區別
Or even get angry. I've never understood the difference.
他永遠不會明白  但同時他又明白一切
He's never understood, yet he understands everything.
拜託  你那顆小小的  自動化的心裏一定有一點憤怒
Come on, there has to be a little anger in that tiny, automated heart of yours.
- 別這樣跟我說話   - 為什麼  你會短路嗎
- Don't talk to me that way!   - Why? Will you short-circuit?
我說了  住手
I said, stop it!
就是這樣
There you go!
- 抱歉   - 你的演算法會讓你很快就完事嗎
- Sorry.   - Was your algorithm faster than you?
我沒有準備好
I wasn't prepared.
那現在你準備好了嗎
And are you prepared for this?
我看  這個傳感器工作得很好嘛
The sensor works rather well, I see.
是的
Yes.
給我看看
Show me.
這就是我的理想老二囉
So that's the cock of my dreams?
顯然是的
Apparently.
你不介意我暫時把你當人看吧
You don't mind if I treat you like a human for a second?
- 你在幹什麼   - 營造一種浪漫的氣氛  我猜
- What are you doing?   - Creating a romantic mood, I guess.
去他媽的你一千七百萬份思維文件中的平庸性幻想
Fuck the pedestrian sexual fantasies of your 17 million mind files!
我刪看到這一切
I want to see it all.
現在和我跳舞
And would it satisfy your longing for originality,
能滿足你對原始的性渴望嗎
to dance with me now?
不  我不想跳舞  我想知道...
No, I don't want to dance. I want to know...
跟你上床是什麼感覺
what it's like to screw you.
嘿
Hey!
- 幹什麼   - 你該睡覺了
- What the hell?   - You should sleep now.
我不應該睡覺
I shouldn't sleep!
我們應該睡在一起
We should sleep together, that's what.
我沒心情  現在時機不對
I'm not in the mood. It's not the right time.
當我說這是一個好時機  這就是一個好時機
It's a good time when I say it's a good time!
- 你是來實現我的願望的   - 沒錯
- You're here to fulfill my wishes.   - Yes, exactly.
- 你就是為此而生的   - 明天見
- You're made for this!   - See you tomorrow.
我命令你留在這裏
I order you to stay here!
我要把你送回工廠
I'll return you to the factory!
- 早上好   - 這絕對不是一個好的早上
- Good morning.   - This is definitely not a good morning.
- 那還有時間來改變這一點   - 湯姆不在這裏
- There's time for that to change.   - Tom's not here.
什麼  他在那兒
What? Where is he?
我看起來像他媽媽嗎  你找不到他嗎
Do I look like his mother? Can't you locate him somehow?
可以找到  但前提是你要報告他失蹤
Yes, but only if you report him missing.
否則的話  你會收到持續監視
Otherwise it would be constant surveillance, of you as well.
這在法律上是不可能的
That's legally impossible.
- 早上好   - 早上好
* Good morning.   - Good morning.
- 你的咖啡裏加牛奶嗎   - 不  謝謝  不過可以加一點糖
- Do you take milk in your coffee?   - No thanks, but maybe a little sugar.
當然  你也要咖啡嗎  艾瑪
Sure. Coffee for you too, Alma?
要的  謝謝
Um, yes. Thanks.
謝謝你
Thank you.
好的  你們現在已經一起度過了
So, you've now spent
兩天三夜
two nights, two days and an additional night together.
你們感覺怎麼樣
How do you feel?
很好
Good.
啊哈
Ah ha.
嗯  是的
Well, yeah.
他...
He's...
他的程序很...
His programming is...
- 有用   - 什麼意思
- It works.   - What do you mean?
你自己也可以看到  他做早餐  他說有意義的話  這很棒
As you can see, he makes breakfast, he says meaningful things, it's great.
你可能沒有意識到  但你對待湯姆就像對待一台機器一樣
You may not realize, but you treat Tom like a machine.
- 是的  我完全意識到了   - 你認為這是為什麼昵
- Yes, I definitely realized that.   - Why do you think that is?
- 因為他就是台機器   - 你是不是低估他了
- Because he is a machine.   - Could you be underestimating him?
湯姆  艾瑪對待你的方式讓你有什麼感覺
Tom, how does Alma's treatment make you feel?
別裝得好像你不知道似的  他什麼都感覺不到
Don't act like you don't know. He can't feel anything.
他沒有感情  他被設計成模仿情感
He has no feelings. He's programmed to simulate emotion.
但是沒有真正的情感
But has no real emotions.
我們為什麼不讓湯姆回答昵
Why don't we let Tom answer?
我覺得艾瑪需要更多的時間
I think Alma needs more time.
根據我們廣泛的分析
According to our extensive analysis,
湯姆是你最有可能幸福相處的伴侶
Tom is the partner you have the best chances of being happy with.
湯姆被設計來滿足我的需要
Tom is programmed to fulfill my needs.
他只是我自己的延伸  你不明白嗎
He's just an extension of my own self. Don't you see?
- 你在戀愛關係中尋求摩擦嗎   - 是的  當然
- Do you seek friction in relationships?   - Yes! Of course I do.
湯姆  你能不能考慮增加摩擦力
Tom, would you consider creating more friction,
- 如果這樣對艾瑪很重要的話  如果她...   - 好吧
- if it's important to Alma? If she...   - Okay.
我受夠了  要麼你是個白癡要麼你也是個機器人
I'm done. Either you're an idiot, or you're a robot as well.
你是機器人嗎
Are you a robot?
湯姆  她是機器人嗎
Tom, is she a robot?
是的
Yes, she is.
難以置信
Unbelievable!
一個糟糕的程序模擬出來的感情心理分析師告訴我
A badly programmed, simulated couples therapist is telling me
- 我應該愛上一個機器人   - 你為什麼不走向那個憤怒...
- that I should fall in love with a robot?   - Why don't you walk toward that anger...
不  你為什麼不從我的公寓裏走出去
No! Why don't you walk right out of my apartment!
告訴你的公司僱傭一個真正的顧問
And tell your company to invest in a real consultant!
或者更新你的系統
Or update your operating system
如果需要你的程序員熬幾個通宵的話
if your programmers are up to a few all-nighters.
- 那個關於系統的話太過分了   - 對不起  但是她真是個笨蛋
- That operating system comment was nasty.   - I'm sorry, but she's a real twit.
我承認她不是我們這個物種最好的代表
I admit she's not the best poster child for our species.
我想道歉
I wanted to apologize
關於昨晚的事
for last night.
我也不是我們種族最好的代表
I wasn't the best poster child for my species either.
你可以告訴她我向你扔東西
You could've told her I threw hard objects at you.
她並沒有問
She didn't ask.
我能幫你找一個新的研究項目嗎  我有一些想法
Can I help you find a new research topic? I have a few ideas.
我們能不能暫時忘記這一切
Can we just forget everything for a day?
楔形文字  論文  評估
Cuneiform, the paper, the evaluation,
你是誰  我是誰
who you are, who I am?
樂意之至
With pleasure.
耐心等下
Just be patient for one second.
但是我渴了
But I'm thirsty!
你沒看見我得幫爺爺嗎
Can't you see I have to help Grandpa?
我不需要任何人的幫助  不要把我當小孩子對待
I don't need help from anybody! Don't treat me like a child!
媽媽
Mama!
我已經八十歲了  我這輩子都在幹這個
I'm 80! I've done it my whole life!
我渴了
I'm thirsty!
- 我只是想讓你穿上...   - 有人嗎  我也想吵吵
- I just want you to put on...   - Hello? I want to fight, too!
爸爸  看看這些污漬  我只是想...
Dad, look at these stains, I just want to...
胡說  我才不脫呢
Nonsense! I won't take them off!
嗨  親愛的  要喝點什麼嗎
Hi, sweetie. Did you want a drink?
讓我們看看有什麼
Let's see what there is.
番茄汁
Tomato juice.
黃瓜汁  菠菜汁
Cucumber juice, spinach juice,
豌豆汁...
pea juice...
好吧  我是認真的
Okay, I'll be serious.
啤酒怎麼樣  酵母啤酒
How about a beer? Yeast beer?
小麥啤酒  蟾蜍啤酒
Wheat beer, toad beer,
蜘蛛啤酒  蝸牛啤酒...
spider beer, snail beer...
- 我要水   - 水嗎
- I want water!   - Water?
這可是個艱巨的任務啊
Now that's a tall order.
- 夠了  把你的褲子穿上...   - 沒有玻璃杯
- That's enough. Put your pants on...!   - There are no glasses.
穿藍褲子我沒意見  只要穿上褲子就行
Put on the blue pants, fine with me! Just put pants on!
沒水了
There's no water!
那就穿棕色的
Then put the brown ones on!
小朋友唱水嗎  還是你要給他們澆水
Do children drink, or do you have to water them?
我不管是那一條  只要穿上褲子就行了
I don't care which pair, just put on some pants!
那裏有個男人
There's a man.
- 那裏   - 那裏
- Where?   - There.
哦  他啊  那不是人  那是機器人
Oh, him. That's not a man, that's a robot.
這是怎麼回事
What's all this about?
- 我要瘋了   - 爺爺  那是個機器人
- I'm going crazy.   - Grandpa, that's a robot.
- 哦  是嗎   - 是的  如果你不穿衣服的話
- Oh?   - Yes, and if you don't get dressed,
我就讓他做你的看護人  他會住在這裏
I'll make him your caregiver and he'll live here.
哦  還是放過我吧
Oh, just leave me alone.
我們想去勒姆島  但那裏很小  只有幾間度假屋
We'd go to Rømø, but it was tiny, just a few vacation houses.
爸爸  附近那個更大的鎮子叫什麼名字
Dad, what was the name of that bigger town nearby?
- 什麼   - 我們買袋裝酸奶的地方
- What?   - Where we bought that yogurt in bags.
這是什麼
What's this?
我們之前在丹麥度過了三個夏天的地方
In Denmark where we spent three summers.
或許是孔斯馬克
Kongsmark, perhaps?
- 是的  孔斯馬克   - 我知道那兒
- Yes! Kongsmark!   - I know it.
- 我父母以前也帶我去過 - 真的嗎
- My parents used to take me there, too.   - Really?
你們都是瘋子
You're all nuts.
阿爾瑪和我會在那裏騎自行車  學校營地後面的沙丘上有乒乓球桌
Alma and I would ride our bikes there. There was this ping-pong table
我們還和一個男孩交了朋友
behind the school camp in the dunes. And we made friends with a boy.
等等  我想我們還有他的照片
Wait, I think we even have a picture of him.
也許那個男孩就是你
Maybe it was you.
他的藍眼睛絕對和你的一樣
He definitely had blue eyes just like yours.
- 他的名字是...   - 哦天  啊
- Was his name...?   - Oh God!
- 他叫托馬斯   - 托馬斯
- His name was Thomas!   - Thomas!
他的名字叫托馬斯
His name was Thomas!
- 當然   - 你還記得我們嗎
- Of course!   - Do you remember us?
我們有一輛紅色的和一輛藍色的自行車  我們都愛上了你
We had a red bike and a blue bike. And we were both in love with you.
- 你也愛上了嗎   - 你愛上誰了
- You, too?   - Who were you in love with?
- 當然啊  我可是你的小妹妹啊   - 你愛上誰了
- Well, I was your little sister!   - Who were you in love with?
機器人
With the robot,
在他小的時候
when he was little.
這個
Here!
這就是他
That's him.
這是你們倆的合照  用我的第一台相機拍的
Here's one of you both, taken with my first camera.
我真的愛上他了
I really was in love with him.
- 但是機器人不會長大   - 你說得太對了
- But robots can't grow.   - You're absolutely right.
我們是人造的  就像汽車一樣
We're manufactured. Like cars.
- 或者洗衣機   - 或者飛機
- Or washing machines.   - Or planes.
我不想再坐飛機了  我都八十歲了
I'm done flying. I'm 80.
- 八十一歲  爸爸   - 在你夢裏吧
- 81, Dad.   - In your dreams.
你不需要飛到任何地方
You don't have to fly anywhere.
八十一歲  八十一歲
81! 81!
爺爺是個笨蛋
Grandpa's a dummy!
我也很想見見你的母親
I would've loved to have met your mother, too.
你還會夢到她嗎
Do you ever still dream about her?
有時候會
Sometimes.
但那是很久以前的事了
But it's so long ago.
我們在...哥本哈根見面的時候
When we met... in Copenhagen,
是什麼樣的情況
what was it like?
在那個糟糕的會議酒店裏
It was at that awful convention hotel.
你坐在講台上  我坐在觀眾席上
You sat on the podium, and I was in the audience.
- 為同事做翻譯   - 在那每個人都會說英語
- Translating for colleagues.   - Everyone speaks English at those things.
但不會說法語  也不會說韓語
But not the French and not the Koreans.
你翻譯成了法語和韓語嗎
You translated into French and Korean?
(公元前1600年至1100年是希臘青銅時代它由伯羅奔尼撤半島的邁錫尼城而得名)
你談到了邁錫尼文明和接下來的黑暗時代
You spoke about Mycenaean culture and the dark centuries that followed.
邁錫尼文明嗎
The Mycenaean culture?
你以為我是知道三千到七千年前事情的專家嗎
Do you think I'm an expert on everything between 3,000 and 7,000 years ago?
(指在西歐歷史上  從西羅馬蒂國的滅亡到文藝復興開始
一段文化層次下降或者社會崩潰的時期)
不是  但絕對是黑暗時代的專家
No, but definitely the dark centuries.
一個鉤鼻子和穿鉤針編織背心的女人採訪了你
And a woman with a striking hook nose and a crocheted vest interviewed you.
什麼  那我會記得她的
What? I would remember her.
你不記得她是因為你只對我有感覺
You can't remember her because you only had eyes for me.
哦  當然
Oh, of course.
- 那為什麼呢    - 因為你在怎...
- Because?   - Because you thought...
後面那個帥哥是誰
who the hell is that good-looking guy in the back?
我們的照片是在那兒拍的  你床邊的那一張
And where was that picture of us taken? The one by your bed?
那是我們第一次去...
That was from our first outing to...
湯姆
Tom
我只是站在那裏  他們並不覺得我很危險
I just stood there. They don't see me as a danger.
我聞起來不像人類
I don't smell like a human.
你聞起來像什麼
What do you smell like, for the deer?
他們甚至不會注意到我  對他們來說我聞起來像是空氣
They don't even notice me. I smell like nothing to them.
我想我們該走了
I think we'd better go.
走到汽車那裏開車回城要花一段時間
It'll take a while to walk to the car and drive back to the city.
我們赤腳跑過草地吧
Let's run across the meadow barefoot.
- 不了   - 來吧
- No!   - Come on.
讓我們體驗一下大自然吧
Let's experience nature!
- 你等等我   - 快點
- Just you wait!   - Come on!
你好
Hello.
你是艾瑪
You're Alma.
我看過照片  我是史黛菲
I've seen photos. I'm Steffi.
- 謝謝你邀請我們   - 不用客氣
- Thanks for inviting us.   - Of course.
- 這是湯姆   - 哦  好的
- This is Tom.   - Oh yes.
- 朱利安告訴過我   - 很高興見到你
- Julian told me.   - It's lovely to meet you.
哇  很老派嘛
Wow, old school!
艾瑪  你真的來了
Alma, you really came!
- 我們真的來了   - 太好了
- We really came.   - Great.
- 你們已經見過了嗎   - 是的
- You've met?   - Yes.
- 你想喝點什麼  白的還是紅的   - 白的
- What would you like to drink? White, red?   - White.
- 莉賈娜  嗨   - 我馬上回來
- Regina, hi!   - I'll be right back.
- 謝謝   - 你已經把照片掛上去了
- Thanks.   - You put the picture up already.
照片掛好了  床也鋪好了  水也接好了
The picture's up, the bed's put together, the water is running.
但還有很多都不能用
But nothing else works yet.
有點奇怪  對吧  一如既往的奇怪
It's a little weird, right? As always.
- 什麼   - 怦  新房子  新生活  新伴侶...
- What?   - Bam! New house, new life, new partner...
怎麼...
What's... ?
哦  上帝
Oh God!
那是誰
Who's that?
他是醫生嗎
Is he a doctor?
是的  他可能也是個醫生
Yes, he's probably a doctor too.
一座房子  一棵樹...
A house, a tree...
希望一份穩定的工作在路上了
and hopefully a steady job on the way!
謝謝
Thanks.
- 艾瑪   - 羅傑
- Alma!   - Roger!
- 他們都在外面   - 布宜諾斯艾利斯的事我很抱歉
- They're all outside.   - I'm so sorry about Buenos Aires.
太令人沮喪了
How frustrating!
湯姆  這是羅傑
Tom, this is Roger.
嗨  也許你還可以使用一部分
Hi. Maybe you can still use some elements
在另一項研究中...
in another study...
那是...
Is that...
太瘋狂了
Crazy.
難以置信
Incredible!
可以碰嗎
May I?
難以置信
Unbelievable.
- 感覺像是...   - 羅傑
- That feels so...   - Roger!
怎麼了
Yes?
- 你知道你在侵犯隱私吧   - 有嗎  只是...
- You do realize you're being invasive?   - Why? It's just....
如果有人碰了你的臉和頭髮  你會有什麼感覺
How would you feel if someone just touched your face and your hair?
我遇到過不上一百次了  但這次不一樣
Well, it's happened to me 100 times, but this is different.
- 怎麼不一樣   - 嗯  這個...
- How?   - Yeah, well...
- 有什麼不同嗎   - 他為什麼不反對  他不能說話嗎
- How is it different?   - Why doesn't he object? Can't he talk?
湯姆也會說話  湯姆是個友好的機器人
Tom can also talk. Tom is a friendly robot.
好吧  現在你完全可以看出差別了
Well, now you can totally tell.
不好意思
Pardon me.
沒問題  我們可以談談
No problem. We'll chat a little.
- 他在耍我嗎   - 是的
- Was he messing with me?   - Yes.
對不起  我情不自禁
Sorry, I couldn't help myself.
- 我能和你談談嗎   - 可以
- Can I talk with you for a second?   - Of course.
哦
Oh.
好吧  跟我來
Yes, come with me.
對不起  這是唯一空著的房間
Sorry, it's the only room that's empty.
告訴我...
Tell me...
史黛菲是懷了孕嗎
Is Steffi pregnant?
媽的
Oh fuck.
我本來想告訴你的  但是...
I was going to tell you anyway, but...
- 很抱歉讓你這樣發現   - 沒關係  現在我知道了
- I'm sorry you found out like this.   - It's fine. Now I know.
她還沒有懷孕三個月  所以你知道...
She's not even three months pregnant yet, so you know...
- 我們還不清楚狀況   - 好的  我知道了
- We're not in the clear yet.   - Yes, I know.
朱利安
Julian?
- 對不起  冰箱裏沒有杜松子酒   - 在冰櫃裏
- Sorry, there's no gin in the fridge.   - In the freezer.
當然  我真蠢
Of course. How dumb of me.
喂  莉賈娜
Regina. Hello.
嗯  一切都很好
Yes, everything's fine.
沒有  只是今天太累了
No, it's just been a long day.
我會的
Yup, I will.
莉賈娜向你問好  她覺得你很棒
Regina says hi. She thinks you're great.
每個人都認為你很棒
Everyone thinks you're great.
除了你
Everyone but you.
我十四歲的時候參加了一個派對
When I was 14, I went to a party.
晚上我一個人坐在陽台上
I sat alone at night on the terrace.
我的同學們在地窖裏跳舞
My classmates were dancing in the cellar.
我看著外面的聯排別墅
I looked out at the townhouses
突然我意識到上帝並不存在
and suddenly I knew that God didn't exist.
然後我成了一個無神論者
And I became an atheist.
當時我對自己發誓
I made a vow to myself back then:
如果我在一架著火的飛機上  我不會祈禱
If I'm in an airplane that's on fire, I'm not going to pray.
我不會向上帝尋求幫助  那怕只是出於恐懼
I won't ask the Lord for help, just out of fear.
因為我不相信上帝
Because I don't believe in God.
你明白嗎
Do you understand?
明白
Yes.
真的嗎
Really?
你不會允許自己因為絕望
You won't allow yourself to become close to a machine
和渴望與人接觸而與機器親近
out of desperation and longing for human contact.
我們之間有鴻溝
There's a gulf between us.
我們可以假裝它不存在
We can pretend it doesn't exist,
假裝幻覺只是現實的另一種形式
pretend the illusion is just another form of reality,
但是有些事情凸顯了這個鴻溝是多麼的深  多麼的不可逾越
but certain things highlight just how deep and insurmountable that gulf is.
- 什麼事   - 你不能理解的事
- What things?   - Things you can't understand.
一些你一想到就讓你傷心的事情
Things that make you sad the second you think of them,
即使你不想去想
even if you don't want to.
一些你渴望或錯過的東西
Things you long for or missed out on
可是再也不會回來了
that will never return.
你能給我看看那些東西嗎
Can you show me these things?
給你看嗎
Show you?
好的  我可以
Yes, I can.
在那邊
Over there.
走遠了
Cold.
接近了
Warmer.
非常接近了
Very warm.
我能打開嗎
Can I open it?
這是胚胎的超聲波圖像
It's the ultrasound image of an embryo.
「艾瑪.費爾瑟  十一週」
"Alma Felser, 11 weeks."
為什麼會覺得我不能理解昵
Why wouldn't I understand?
你失去了一個孩子
You've lost a child.
在你這個年齡  你可能有機率不會再有第二個孩子了
At your age, you probably won't be able to have another one.
你難過是因為你想體驗這種感覺
You're sad because you would've liked to have experienced that.
你覺得被拋棄了
You feel cast aside
因為朱利安又要生孩子了  而他會忘記這個孩子
because Julian is having another baby and will forget this one.
也許你會想起你的父親  你可能會像他一樣孤獨終老
Maybe you think of your father, that you might end up as lonely as he is
你甚至不會有孩子來照顧你
and you won't even have children to take care of you.
我能理解  這很容易理解
I can understand that. It's very easy to understand.
你說這話的時候  聽起來像是很無關緊要
It sounds banal when you say it.
無關緊要  自我放縱  可悲
Banal and self-indulgent and pathetic.
這很可悲
It is pathetic.
你的痛苦是可悲的  因為它是相對的
Your pain is pathetic because it's relative.
但也不可悲
But it's also not pathetic,
因為它是你的一部分  這就是我喜歡它的原因
because it's part of you, and that's why I love it.
- 我一直在找你   - 你怎樣進來的
- I was looking for you.   - How did you get in here?
我是一台電腦  門鎖定系軌也是一台電胭
I'm a computer. The lock system is a computer.
我們偶爾會互相幫助
We help each other out once in a while.
- 真的嗎   - 不是
- Really?   - No.
我拿了你的備用卡
I took your spare card.
因為我知道我會在這裏找到你
Because I knew I'd find you here.
是這樣嗎
Is that so?
如果人們乘坐的飛機即將墜毀  大多數人都會祈禱
Most people would pray if their airplane was about to crash.
這是人之常情
It's human to do that.
如果你願意  可以想像是在和一個人類
Think of a human if you'd like.
你可以想像是在和一個機器人
And you can think of a robot.
高潮是什樣感覺
What does it feel like to have an orgasm?
就像...就像是溶解一樣
It's... It's like dissolving.
你溶解  然後...
You dissolve and...
成為某個更大事件的一部分
you're part of something bigger.
哦  這咖啡聞起來真香
Oh, does that coffee smell good!
我打呼嚕了嗎
Was I snoring?
我覺得我打呼嚕了  是不是很奇怪
I think I was snoring. Isn't that strange?
這樣不行
This isn't working.
這是錯的  我不能這麼做
It's all wrong. I can't do this.
做什麼
Do what?
我替你拉起被子  即使你不會感冒
I pull the covers up for you, even though you can't get cold.
即使你不睡覺  我也攝手攝腳地走出房間
I tiptoe out of the room, even though you don't sleep.
我試著給你做一個完美的煮雞蛋
I try to make you a perfect boiled egg,
即使你不在乎它是硬的還是軟的
even though you could care less if it's hard or soft boiled.
你甚至不用吃東西
You don't even have to eat.
我正在演一齣戲
I'm acting in a play.
但是沒有觀眾
But there's no audience.
所有的座位都是空的
All the seats are empty.
我根本不是為你演戲
I'm not even acting for you.
我很孤獨  我是在為我自己演戲
I'm all alone. I'm only acting for myself.
即使是現在  我也只是在自言自語
Even right now, I'm only talking to myself.
這並不是在對話
It's not a dialogue.
我正在變成一個怪人  一個瘋子
I'm turning into a lunatic, a nutcase,
...一個咧著嘴笑的白癡  這必須停止
...a grinning idiot and this has to stop.
你為什麼哭
Why are you crying?
我哭是因為昨晚太...
I'm crying because last night was so...
美好了  而且...
beautiful, and...
人類不是說過愛是沒有界限的嗎
Don't humans say: "love knows no bounds"?
那麼一直都是謊言
That's always been a lie.
但是我能去那兒呢
But where am I to go?
- 我要提前結束實驗   - 好的  但是...
- I'm ending the experiment early.   - Yes, but...
我該去那兒
Where am I to go?
我怎麼知道  也許去工廠
How should I know? The factory, maybe?
你可以把鑰匙留一段時間  以後再給我
You can keep the keys for a while. Give them to me later.
我想我不需要你的鑰匙了
I doubt I'll be needing your keys.
- 沒事的  但也許...   - 艾瑪...
- Yeah, but maybe...   - Alma...
我將不再存在了
I won't exist anymore.
我要回去了
I'm going back.
- 然後我就會被抹去   - 哦  天啊
- Then I'll be erased.   - Oh God!
- 聽起來像是...   - 這就是不活著的好處
- That sounds like...   - That's an advantage of not being alive.
你也不會死
You can't die either.
別擔心我
Don't worry about me.
湯姆
Tom!
我不能把你送走
I can't send you away.
你必須為我這樣做
You have to do it for me.
你的演算法必須為我做到這一點
Your algorithm has to do it for me.
我不會讓你走的
I wouldn't let you go.
你他媽的是白癡嗎
Are you a fucking idiot?
別盯著我  你這個婊子
Stop staring, you bitch!
怎麼回事
What?
爸爸  怎麼了
Dad! What happened?
你在幹什麼
What are you doing?
我在找遙控器
I'm looking for the remote control.
就在這附近
It's around here somewhere.
- 你不能找找嗎   - 你怎麼流血了
- Can't you look for it?   - Why are you bleeding?
- 來吧  爸爸  我帶你回家   - 但遙控器
- Come on, Dad. I'll bring you home.   - But the remote!
它一定在這裏的某個地方
It has to be here somewhere.
我敢肯定在家裏  我們回家再找找吧
I'm sure it's at home. We'll look for it at home.
它一定在這裏的什麼地方  也許掉了在什麼東西後面
It must be here somewhere. Maybe it fell behind something.
目前就這些
That's it for now.
誰會這樣做
Who would do this?
毆打一個穿著睡衣的困惑老人
Beat up a confused, old man in his nightshirt.
業餘的
Amateurs.
絕對是業餘的  像是癮君子  絕望的人
Definitely amateurs: junkies, desperate people.
- 保重   - 這裏經常發生這種事
- Take care.   - Happens a lot around here.
過去六個月有十二個這樣的案子了
12 cases in the last six months.
專業的會發現這裏沒什麼值錢的東西
A pro would see there's nothing valuable here.
什麼沒有值錢的東西  這裏的東西都很值錢
Nothing valuable? Everything here is valuable.
你知道這些照片有多值錢嗎
Do you have any idea how valuable this all is? Every photo?
這些都很值錢
It's all valuable!
- 你怎麼能這樣說   - 對不起  我...
- How could you say that?   - I'm sorry, I...
我的意思是  從一個小偷的角度來看  價值總是相對的
I meant, from a thief's perspective. Value is always relative.
哦  天啊
Oh God!
大家好
Hello.
- 早上好   - 早上好
- Good morning.   - Good morning.
很高興見到你們
It's nice to see you all.
你需要什麼嗎
Hey, you need anything?
你好
Hello?
打擾一下
Excuse us.
請允許我介紹一下  這位是克洛伊
May I introduce you? This is Chloé.
你好  我是克洛伊
Hello, I'm Chloé.
我們在舞廳的活動見過
From the event in the ballroom?
我也是個專家  但是在司法系統
I'm an expert too, but in the judicial system.
斯圖博士
Dr Stuber.
克洛伊是...
And Chloé is...?
她是我的唯一
She's my one and only.
你不能一直這麼說
You mustn't keep saying that.
- 進展如何   - 進展如何
- And how is it going?   - How is it going?
我不知道應該怎樣形容
I don't know how to describe it.
我從來不知道能夠這麼快樂
I had no idea it was possible to be this happy.
當然  我是個老傢伙  我的身體...  畢竟我已經六十二歲了
I'm an old fart, of course. My body... I'm 62 after all.
但現在我和克洛伊在一起了
But now that I'm with Chloé,
我知道我以前是多麼不開心
I see just how unhappy I was before.
沒人要我
Nobody wanted me.
我身上有種特質  讓人們總是躲著我
There's something about me. People run from me.
我不知道為什麼  也許是因為外激素或者我的外表
I don't know why. Maybe it's pheromones or my appearance.
我整個人生都是這樣
It was like that my entire life.
我已經習慣了  也本會這樣一直下去  但是...
I'd gotten used to it. That's just the way it was, but...
我現在和克洛依在一起... 她比任何人都要對我好
now with Chloé... She's kinder to me than any human ever was.
你應該得到善待
You deserve to be treated kindly.
我已經在談判  看在什麼條件下我可以留下她
I'm already in negotiations to see under what conditions I could keep her.
你呢  你和...
And you? How are you and...
你和...
You and...
親愛的羅傑
Dear Roger,
這是我答應過的評估報告
here is my evaluation as promised.
祝你一切順利  艾瑪
All the best, Alma.
人類歷史充滿了所謂的進步
Human history is full of supposed improvements
其可怕的後果在幾十年甚至幾個世紀後才變得清晰
whose dire consequences only become clear decades or even centuries later.
在我與一個名為湯姆的類人機器人的相處之後
After my experience with a humanoid robot named Tom,
我可以肯定地說
I can say with certainty
一個被設計來取代丈夫或妻子的機器人
that a robot designed to replace a husband or wife
就是這樣一個所謂的改進
is one such supposed improvement.
毫無疑問  一個類人機器人是根據個人喜好定製的
There's no doubt that a humanoid robot tailored to individual preferences
不僅可以取代伴侶
can not only replace a partner,
甚至可以看起來是更好的伴侶
but can even seem to be the better partner.
他們可以滿足我們的渴望
They fulfill our longings,
滿足我們的慾望
satisfy our desires
消除我們的孤獨感
and eliminate our feeling of being alone.
他們讓我們快樂
They make us happy.
快樂又有什麼錯呢
And what could be wrong with being happy?
- 早上好   - 啊  什麼事
- Good morning.   - Ah. Yes?
雖然我不可能更新我的操作系統
Although it's not possible to update my operating system,
我的通訊區域已經被重組了
my communication sector has been restructured.
什麼
What?
我相信今天的會議一定會很成功
I'm sure we'll have a successful session today.
- 湯姆不在這裏   - 他什麼時候回來
- Tom is not here.   - When will he be back?
他不在你公司嗎
He's not at your company?
他為什麼會在那裏
Why would he be?
但是人類真的打算
But are humans really intended
只需按下按鈕就能夠滿足他們所有的需求嗎
to have all their needs met at the push of a button?
難道不是因為我們未滿足的渴望
Is it not our unfulfilled longing,
我們的想像力和對幸福無止境的追求
our imagination and our unending pursuit of happiness
才是我們人性的泉源嗎
that are the sources of our humanity?
如果我們允許類人機器作為配偶  我們將創造一個由癮君子組成的社會
If we allow humanoids as spouses, we will create a society of addicts,
因為他們的需求會被永久地滿足  並從持續不斷的個人承認中得到滿足
gorged and weary from having their needs permanently met
他們會變得貪婪和疲憊
and from a constant flow of personal acknowledgement.
我們會有什麼動力去面對傳統的個人
What impetus would we have to confront conventional individuals,
去挑戰自我  去忍受衝突  去改變昵
to challenge ourselves, to endure conflicts, to change?
可以預見的是  任何長期與類人機器生活在一起的人
It's to be expected that anyone who lives with a humanoid long term
都會變得無法維持正常的人類接觸
will become incapable of sustaining normal human contact.
所以我強烈反對
I strongly advise against
批准類人機器作為生活伴侶
authorizing humanoids as life partners.
- 你在這裏坐了多久   - 沒多久
- How long have you been sitting here?   - Not that long.
三天
Three days.
但我步行來這裏花了不少時間
I came here on foot. It took a while.
你打算在這裏等多久
How long were you going to wait?
直到你到來
Until you came.
我希望我從來沒有遇見過你
I wish I'd never met you.
沒有你的生活就是現在這樣沒有你的生活
Life without you is now just a life without you.
這不就是你所說的愛的定義嗎
Isn't that the definition of what you call love?
我總是躺在乒乓球桌的這一邊
I'd always lie on this side of the ping-pong table.
我不知道為什麼  但是我比較喜歡這一面
I don't know why, but I liked this side much better than the other one.
托馬斯總是蹦蹦跳跳地穿過沙丘
Thomas was always jumping up and running through the dunes.
有時你能聽到他的聲音  有時卻聽不到
Sometimes you'd hear him, sometimes you wouldn't.
我不記得柯拉去了那裏
I don't remember where Cora was.
我非常愛他
I was so in love with him.
愛到我幾乎無法承受
I could hardly bare it.
當他在沙丘上追趕鵪鶉
While he was chasing partridges through the dunes,
或埋石頭  或尋找琥珀
or burying stones, or hunting for amber,
或丹麥男孩在沙丘上做的任何事情時
or whatever it is Danish boys do in dunes,
我總是閉著睛躺在這裏
I'd always lie here with my eyes closed,
希望他能吻我
hoping that he'd kiss me.
有幾次我非常肯定
And a few times I was absolutely positive
他的臉正對著我
that his face was right over mine.
我能在我的嘴唇上感覺到他的呼吸
I could feel his breath on my lips.
但當我睜開眼睛
But when I opened my eyes,
我獨自一人
I was alone,
而托馬斯卻不見蹤影
and Thomas was nowhere in sight.